A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller photographs, Albums, RG 2 FA1128A FA1128A
Rockefeller Archive Center
Laurance S. Rockefeller photographs, Albums, RG 2
1910 - 1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
FA1128A
41 Cubic Feet
Arrangement
RG 2, LSR Photographs – Albums, is sorted into two parallel series, according to album size. Within each series (Large or Small), albums are arranged into the numerical subject categories that are used throughout the collection:
000 Art, 100 Family, 200 Houses, 300 Miscellaneous, 400 Civic, 500 Travel, 600 Resorts.
The albums are then numbered within these categories and given a numerical tag that includes both the category number and an album number (e.g., Large Album, 100-1). Some categories (Houses, Travel, and Resorts) are further subdivided to indicate geographic or other distinctions, such as the location of houses or the names of resorts (e.g., Small Album, 600-M3, pertains to the Mauna Kea resort). The Letter abbreviations are explained in the series notes.
LSR's curators also assigned a unique Accession Number to each album. We have included this number in a Scope and Contents note for each album. LSR's album indexes, as well as album-print, negative, and contact-sheet files in FA1128D, generally refer to albums by their Accession Number alone.
In a few cases, albums are arranged by subject category but are lacking a specific album number and/or an accession number. These albums are labeled by category and are then numbered "0" or described as "unnumbered." These unnumbered albums were generally later additions to the collection.
Biographical / Historical
Laurance Spelman Rockefeller was born on May 26, 1910, in New York City, the fourth of the six children of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He attended Lincoln School, a progressive coeducational preparatory school connected with Teachers College of Columbia University in New York City, before entering Princeton in 1928. A philosophy major, he graduated from Princeton in 1932 with a B.A. degree in philosophy and went on to two years of graduate study at Harvard Law School.
On August 15, 1934, Laurance Rockefeller married Mary French in the Congregational Church in Woodstock, Vermont. Together they raised three daughters and a son.
During World War II, Laurance Rockefeller served in the Navy (1942-1945), attaining the rank of lieutenant commander.
Laurance Rockefeller pursued a number of successful careers during his lifetime. He was a pioneer in the field of venture capital. He was a leading and influential figure for three decades in the American conservation movement. He led the development of one of the world's foremost cancer care and research facilities, and was both a benefactor and advisor to major educational institutions. And, with great foresight, he combined his personal vision for conservation, recreation, and the spiritual needs of individuals to develop internationally acclaimed environmentally oriented resorts. His many accomplishments have been recognized both nationally and internationally.
In 1935, he began working in the family office in Rockefeller Center. His first duties were to develop his knowledge and understanding of Rockefeller philanthropic activities, conservation projects, and business interests, through both study and playing a modest role in their operation. Simultaneously, he developed his own special interest, blending business acumen with the talents of a "gadgeteer," a label he once pinned on himself.
He became well known as an investor of risk capital in young enterprises whose future was based primarily on scientific and technological developments. Over the years his investment interests included the fields of aviation, aerospace, electronics, high temperature physics, composite materials, optics, lasers, data processing, thermionics, instrumentation, and nuclear power. Beginning in August 1969, his venture capital investments in these areas were made through a venture capital group, Venrock, formed by members of the Rockefeller family.
In a different area of venture capital, he developed outstanding environmentally oriented resort hotels in Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hawaii, and Vermont, serving as chairman of Rockresorts, Inc., a resort management company which he founded and chaired.
Conservation of the environment and recreational development constituted much of Laurance Rockefeller's philanthropy and public service. His introduction to public service came in 1939 when Governor Herbert H. Lehman of New York appointed him to the Palisades Interstate Park Commission (PIPC). He was president of the PIPC from 1970 to 1977 and continued as a commissioner until his resignation in December 1978. He was an advisor to Presidents Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon, and Ford on matters of environmental conservation and outdoor recreation, and he worked on federal commissions set up to help develop national conservation and environmental policies and programs. In 1958, President Dwight D. Eisenhower appointed him chairman of the Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission (ORRRC), which charted ways of meeting the nation's outdoor recreation needs through the year 2000. He was a special emissary for President Lyndon Johnson in the effort that led to creation of the National Redwoods Park in California, and he served as chairman of President Nixon's Citizens' Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, successor to a similar group which he headed under President Johnson. He played a pivotal role in the creation and development of several national parks including Grand Teton National Park in Wyoming, Virgin Islands National Park on the island of St. John, and Marsh-Billings-Rockefeller National Historical Park in Vermont.
He served as a leader of several important nonprofit and philanthropic organizations. He was president and later chairman of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1958-1980) and was a trustee of the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation (1960-1982). His first association with Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York City was in 1947; he also served as chairman (1960-1982), overseeing an expansion and modernization of its operations. He was a longtime trustee of the New York Zoological Society (1935-1986) and served as its president (1969-1971) and chairman (1971-1985).
Laurance Rockefeller received many honors for his efforts on behalf of the environment and cancer research and treatment. Among them are the Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. Memorial Award from the American Cancer Society (1969), the Medal of Freedom (1969), Commander (Honorary) of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (1971), the Woodrow Wilson Award from Princeton University (1991), the Congressional Gold Medal (1991), the Chairman's Award from the National Geographic Society (1995), the Theodore Roosevelt National Park Medal of Honor (1995), and the Lady Bird Johnson Conservation Award for Lifetime Achievement (1997). In 2003, he became the first person to be made an honorary citizen of the British Virgin Islands in recognition of his many contributions to the area. In December 1959 he received the National Institute of Social Sciences' Gold Medal for distinguished services to humanity, an award previously bestowed upon his grandfather and father. This was the first time in the Institute's history that three generations of a family had been so honored. The citation to Laurance Rockefeller proclaimed him as a "creative organizer of ventures into new fields of human endeavor for the growing aspirations of mankind; [and a] leader in the conservation of natural resources and in the development of the medical and social sciences for the welfare of the individual." In 1967, the National Institute awarded Gold Medals to all five Rockefeller brothers in recognition of their individual and collective services to humanity.
Laurance Rockefeller died on July 11, 2004, at his home in Manhattan.
Prepared by Rockefeller Family and Associates, June 1982, and 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (CDs) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
From an early age, Laurance S. Rockefeller (LSR) was an avid photographer, and his photograph collection reflects this appreciation, along with the broad range of his activities and interests. The LSR Photographs collection is sorted into several component groupings, loosely based on format, storage location (home or office), or use (e.g., Photo Reference files), at the time his collection was arranged and catalogued.
RG 2 (FA1128A) contains LSR's photo Albums (dating mainly up to the mid-1980s, when LSR's curators catalogued the collection). The albums are sorted into two series according to size, and are then arranged by subject category. Some albums are formal photograph albums, containing a series of portraits, or documenting particular objects, occasions, trips, or moments in time. Other albums are more miscellaneous in their contents and the circumstances of their creation. LSR routinely selected images for printing or enlargement from among his slides and negatives, and created albums from them. As of 1986, the albums were housed together in LSR's apartment at 834 Fifth Avenue.
The photo albums in RG 2 (FA1128A), document LSR's personal and family life from childhood through retirement, as well as many of his business and civic activities. Albums cover various art collections; childhood and family portraits, and multiple family occasions; houses, friends, and family, in New York, Vermont, and Wyoming; civic, social, and business activities and occasions; travel in Europe, Mexico, and the U. S.; LSR's yachts and voyages upon them; and his resort developments, particularly in the Caribbean, Puerto Rico, and Hawaii.
The other component groupings of the LSR Photographs collection are: RG 1 (FA1128), which contains LSR's loose or "flat" photo files, plus materials that were not included in other collection components at the time the collection was organized; RG 3 (FA1128B), LSR's Slide Books; RG 4 (FA1128C), LSR's Snapshot Files; and RG 5 (FA1128D), LSR's Photo Reference Files. RG 5 (FA1128D) also includes a subject index to LSR's albums, as well as duplicate Album prints, and an Album Negatives file.
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
- Large, 1910 - 1990s; 1
  - 000 - Art, 1
    - 000-1, Vases, Undated; Color 8x10 photographs in leather ring binder (Box A 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Vases and some porcelain or china sets. (LSR Album Accession number: 86.)
    - 000-2, Sterling Silver Collection, Undated; Black and white, 3x5 photographs. Large postbound album, missing front cover. (Box A 2)
      Photos numbered 1-258, and 1T-38T. (LSR Album Accession number 85.)
    - 000-3, JY Indian Basket Collection, 1965; 8x10 mainly black and white photos in full ring binder. Tags identifying items CRFT number are well glued on to page protectors but could come loose in future. (Box A 3)
      JY Indian Basket Collection identified by their placement at JY Ranch, bought in 1965. Photos by room, with numbered identification of baskets. Also some blackware pottery and artwork. (LSR Album Accession number 88.)
    - 000-4, JY Indian Basket Collection, 1965; 8x10 mainly black and white photos in full ring binder. Tags identifying items CRFT number are well glued on to page protectors but could come loose in future. (Box A 1)
      JY Indian Basket Collection identified by their placement at JY Ranch. Photos by room, with numbered identification of baskets and some commentary. Also some blackware pottery and artwork. Some color photos inserted under page protectors. (LSR Album Accession number 89.)
    - 000-5, JY Navajo Rug Collection, 1965; 8x10 black and white and color photos in full ring binder. CRFT numbers glued on to page protectors. (Box A 4)
      JY Navajo Rug Collection identified by their placement at JY Ranch. Photos, attached numbers, and some commentary. (LSR Album Accession number 91.)
    - 000-6, JY Navajo Rug Collection, 1965 (Box A 5)
      JY Navajo Rug Collection identified by their placement at JY Ranch. Photos, attached numbers, and some commentary. Continuation of album 000-5. (LSR Album Accession number 92.)
  - 100 - Family, 1910 - 1990s; 2
    - 100-0, LSR Photographs, 1923-1924; Childhood album with photos and captions by LSR. Leather album, black paper pages, string bound. Somewhat fragile. (Box A 6)
      Trip west (Grand Canyon, Arizona, New Mexico, Yellowstone); Seal Harbor; LSR pony and awards; England, France; Babs and NAR cross-dressing; Ormond Beach. (LSR Album Accession number 226.)
    - 100-1, Billings Family Album, Photostatic pages of photographs and text, in oversized ringbound album. Multiple copies, bound and unbound, in LSR collection. (Box A 7)
      Photographic history of Billings family, up to 1947, including MFR and family. (LSR Album Accession number 221.)
    - 100-2, MFR album, 1934-1950s; Mainly black and white 8x10 photos (Box A 8)
      LSR - MFR wedding; LSR and Larry portraits; DR wedding; LSR family portrait, mid-1940s; 5 brothers at 5600; MFR with 3 girls; LSR family with actress in buckskin; JY; MFR in period dress. (LSR Album Accession number 93.)
    - 100-3, 1930s-1940s; Black and white, photos slipping, pages not holding (Box A 9)
      MFR and LSR hunting, girls in sandbox, LSR-MFR at party, Vermont, Pocantico; children with nurse, with LSR, pets. (LSR Album Accession number 36.)
    - 100-4, 1940s; black and white photos. (Box A 9)
      MFR with 3 girls, Laura on pony, Christmas, MFR with infant, JDR Jr. and AAR with sons (WR in uniform). August 1946: color snapshots JY, Laura and Marion on horseback. (LSR Album Accession number 37.)
    - 100-5, 1936-1940s; Large album, front cover detached; photo pages badly deteriorated - paper crumbling, adhesive edging coming undone - pages open. Photos are loose on pages - album should perhaps be dismantled. (Box A 10)
      Formal portraits of children and MFR with children; includes portrait of MFR. (LSR Album Accession number 94.)
    - 100-6, LSR and MFR family and grandchildren, 1958-1983; Oversized album, mainly color snapshots. Pages crumpled (Box A 11)
      JY Ranch, New York, and Vermont. (LSR Album Accession number 208.)
    - 100-7, Lucy and Charles Hamlin, 1964; 8x10 color (Box A 11)
      Album of informal photos taken at various times, with husband (LSR Album Accession number 50.)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Material in the Rockefeller family collections that concerns the activities of living members of the Rockefeller family is restricted.
    - 100-8, LSR and MFR and family, 1967-1968; Magnetic album of color snapshots; photos slipping out. (Box A 12)
      Pocantico, Vermont, Europe, Caribbean (possibly on Sea Star), Thanksgiving 1967-January 1968 and undated. (LSR Album Accession number 212.)
    - 100-9, LSR and MFR family and grandchildren, 1979; Color snapshots, stamped November 1979. Photos coming loose from pages. (Box A 13)
      Vermont wagon rides; JY Ranch, including Red Mathews. (LSR Album Accession number 95.)
    - 100-10, LSR and MFR "Annivirthday," August 15, 1980, 10 color snapshots; Pages unglued - photos loose. (Box A 13)
      LSR and MFR 46th anniversary celebration at the JY Ranch. (LSR Album Accession number 209.)
    - 100-11, 1980; Color snapshots (Box A 13)
      Christmas 1980, at Laura Chasin's house. MFR, grandchildren, NYC scenes in snow, aerial photos around NYC. (LSR Album Accession number 96.)
    - 100-13, Rockefeller Family Reunion, June 19, 1983, 1983 June 19; Oversized album, 4x6 color prints (Box A 14)
      At Kykuit. (LSR Album Accession number 97.)
    - 100-14, LSR and MFR Fiftieth-Anniversary Party at JY Ranch, 1984 August 15; Oversized album, 4x6 color prints (Box A 14)
      Note inside cover from Ruth Haupert to Fred Smith, enclosing the album.
    - 100-15, Laura Rockefeller Chasin's Fiftieth-Birthday Celebration, Woodstock, October 11-13, 1986, 1986 October; Color snapshots in magnetic album (Box A 15)
      Woodstock mansion and Billings Farm. (LSR Album Accession number 228.)
    - 100-17, LSR Childhood Album, 1910-1920s; Glued to album pages. In good condition, but some transfer to pages. (Box A 16)
      LSR formal portraits from infancy to teen. Include sibling groups and formal family portraits. (LSR Album Accession number not found.)
    - LSR Childhood Album, 1910-1920s; Small photos cut and glued to pages of leather bound "Laurence" album. Some photos are faded. (Box A 17)
      LSR informal portraits from infancy to teen. Siblings at work and play, posed groups, school plays, ponies, swimming, boating, etc.
    - LSR Seventieth-Birthday Album of Favorite Songs, 1980 May 26; Items attached to pages in oversized ringbound album (Box A 18)
      Album of themed sheet music and family photographs and clippings, assembled for LSR's 70th birthday. Includes list of LSR's favorite songs.
    - Lucy, Jacob, and Naomi Waletzky at Caneel Bay, late 1980s-1990s; Oversized album with 30 4x6 color prints (Box A 18)
      During Christmas. Includes photo of LSR and MFR. Identification written on envelope of negatives enclosed in album.
  - 200 - Houses, 1937-1987; 3
    Arrangement
    Albums within the 200, Houses, series are grouped by geographic location: N = New York; V = Vermont; W = Wyoming (JY Ranch and Valley Ranch).
    - 200-N1, 4 and 10 West 54th Street, 1937; Black and white photos in ringbound album. (Box A 19)
      Oversized photographs of exteriors and interiors and furnishings. Presumably by Gottsho, but not same selection of photographs as in 200 N1 (2). (LSR Album Accession number 98.)
    - 200-N1 (copy 2), 4 and 10 West 54th Street, NY, 1937; Portfolio of printed photographs (Box A 19)
      Samuel Gottscho photos in portfolio album, of interiors and furnishings of JDR Jr.'s and AAR's residence. (LSR Album Accession number 99.)
    - 200-N2, 740 Park Avenue, 1940s; Oversized ringbound album of black and white photos (Box A 20)
      Oversized album of interiors and furnishings. Includes 2 group photos of family: 1) NAR, Happy, and 2 sons; DR and Peggy; Babs; LSR and MFR. 2) LSR, NAR, WR, DR, and 2 unidentified men, standing under portrait of JDR Jr. (LSR Album Accession number 100.)
    - 200-N3, Views, possibly from 834 Fifth Ave, 1980s; Color photos 8x10 and 5x7, in 3 ring binder (Box A 21)
      LSR, aerial views of NY skyscrapers, Central Park Zoo, Rockefeller University from the river, etc. (LSR Album Accession number 101.)
    - 200-N4, Saranac Lake Camp (Camp Canaras), 1960s; Color snapshots 3x5 in 3 ring binder (Box A 21)
      Sign in photo identifies property as "Canaras, St. Lawrence University Conference Center." (LSR Album Accession number 102.)
    - 200-N5, The Rockefeller Family Estate at Pocantico Hills, Christmas 1980, 1980 December (Box A 22)
      Large, Bound album of printed photos of Kykuit interiors and grounds. Photo attributions inside cover. (LSR Album Accession number 153.)
    - 200-V1, Woodstock Mansion interiors, Undated; 8x10 professional color shots in ringbound album (Box A 23)
      LSR Album Accession number 215.
    - 200-V2, Woodstock, 1980s; Mainly snapshots. In oversized magnetic album, some photos slipping. (Box A 24)
      Family wedding in Maine; French Family Reunion, Woodstock; Calvin Coolidge's homestead. Billings Farm and Museum; Woodstock with grandchildren; group photos. (LSR Album Accession number 103.)
    - 200-W2, JY Ranch, 1978; Color 3x5 snapshots (Box A 25)
      LSR and Mamdouha Bobst at JY Ranch. (LSR Album Accession number 106.)
    - 200-W3, JY Ranch, Valley Ranch Construction, 1982; Flip album with 4x6 color shots; some photos slipping out. (Box A 25)
      MFR, LSR, guests; painting by lake, landscapes, Valley House construction. (LSR Album Accession number 104.)
    - 200-W4, JY Ranch, Valley Ranch Construction, 1982; color 4x6 snapshots (Box A 24)
      MFR painting by lake, canoeing, new construction (LSR and MFR), golf, elk or moose in landscape. (LSR Album Accession number 109.)
    - 200-W5, Valley Ranch, Colter Bay Museum, JDR Jr. Parkway, 1982; color 4x6 prints, magnetic album (Box A 24)
      LSR,MFR, children and grandchildren. (LSR Album Accession number 115.) Also includes Billings Farm and Museum in Woodstock, VT?
    - 200-W6, Valley House, 1983 May; 4x6 color photos in magnetic album. Intact, but some page deterioration. (Box A 26)
      Floor plan and interior shots, with captions and tagging of carpets. (LSR Album Accession number 112.)
    - 200-W7, Valley Ranch House, 1983 May; Oversized magnetic album - many pages are labeled but without photographs. Some photos slipping. (Possibly a preliminary album to number W6) (Box A 26)
      Interior shots, especially of rugs and baskets. Some rooms seem barely furnished. Includes a few shots of LSR and MFR.(LSR Album Accession number 111.)
    - 200-W8, JY Ranch, Valley Ranch House, 1984 April; 3x5 color snapshots (Box A 27)
      JY in winter. Elk, MFR, Valley House interiors and exterior, basket collection; golfing (possibly Arizona). (LSR Album Accession number 107.)
    - 200-W9, LSR and MFR Fiftieth-Anniversary Party at JY Ranch, 1984 August 15; mainly 5x7 color photos in Large Magnetic album. Some photos slipping. (Box A 27)
      MFR, LSR, family, grandchildren, and friends. MFR, LSR, DR on horseback. (LSR Album Accession number 105.)
    - 200-W10, LSR and MFR Fiftieth-Anniversary Party at JY Ranch, 1984 August 15; 3x5 color snapshots (Box A 27)
      Family and guests; rafting trip; candids and groups; landscape and flowers; house. (LSR Album Accession number 110.)
    - 200-W11, JY Ranch, 1987 July-September (Box A 28)
      Landscape, horses, arch made from elk horn; visit by Mr. and Mrs. Frank Borman, September 1987; rowing on lake; October 1987 note from Mary Ellen and Bill, and photos of unidentified guests. LSR, MFR, Larry R. (LSR Album Accession number 235.)
  - 300 - Miscellaneous, 1929-1988; 4
    - 300-1, 1929-1963; Oversized, miscellaneous album, mainly color snapshots, but some black and white 8x10 photos, LSR and others (Box A 29)
      Princeton summer camp, AAR and DR, LSR with unidentified person, reviewing map; Sea Star; Europe; JY; LSR presenting horseshoe plaque; LSR and MFR in Caribbean, Jolly Roger boat; Mildred Layne party, 1967; Caribbean and shipboard on Sea Star; LSR and MFR, Niagara State Parks Commission, 1963. (LSR Album Accession number 27.)
    - 300-2, 1940-1959; 3-ring album, mainly black and white 8x10. Anthony Wayne photos have identifications on back. Naval photos sent to LSR by a Capt. Vande Water. (Box A 30)
      Naval service - inspection visits, 1940s; Caneel Bay (LSR and aerial views); inspection of Anthony Wayne Recreation Center, 1955; informal portraits of LSR and siblings, 1950s; Eastern Air Lines Board, with Rickenbacker, 1940s-early 1950s; MFR, 1940s (LSR Album Accession number 187.)
    - 300-3, 1950-1981; Fabric covered large magnetic album; mainly 8x10 color, some black and white (Box A 31)
      Pocanctico, Resorts, Civic. Woodstock aerial; visit of Queen to Little Dix; LSR; Mauna Kea aerials; LSR, MFR, by portrait of JDR Jr.; JFK and signing ceremony for Bureau of Outdoor Recreation (1963); NAR on beach with unidentified; Hau Tree Terrace plaque, 1975; LSR with leis; Mrs. Bobst; Sea Star published photo; Sinatra benefit 1980. (LSR Album Accession number 113.)
    - 300-4, 1960s-1980s; Mainly color snapshots in fabric covered magnetic album. (Box A 32)